Guide to the Thomas Egleston Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Thomas Egleston Papers
1857-1901.
Egleston, Thomas, 1832-1900.
4.5 linear ft. (2 document boxes, 1 flat box)
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027
MS#0385
4078728
Biographical Note
Thomas Egleston was a noted metallurgist and professor of metallurgy and mineralogy at Columbia University's School of Mines, which he helped found along with Charles F. Chandler and Francis Vinton in 1864.
Egleston was born in New York City in 1900 and received his scientific training first at Yale, and then at the Ecole Imperiale des Mines in Paris. He worked for several years at the Smithsonian Institute before returning to New York City to join the faculty of Columbia University.
He was instrumental in founding the Columbia University School of Mines, one of the earliest schools devoted to practical and applied science in the country. He continued to teach at Columbia until his death in 1900.
Scope and Content
Professional correspondence of Egleston, consisting of incoming letters and technical reports relating to mining engineering and metallurgy; and carbon copies of correspondence between Egleston and Seth Low for the years 1890 to 1900.
The 1996 addition the collection consists of large drawings and engravings from his student days at the Ecole Imperiale des Mines in Paris (both engineering and architecture) as well as large maps of coal and iron land in Virginia and West Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1868-1901
Series II: Research and Documents, undated and 1868
Series III: Metric System Materials, 1893-1895
Subjects
Columbia College (New York, N.Y.).--School of Mines.; Ecole nationale supérieure des mines de Paris.; Chalmers, William James, 1852-1938.; Church, John A. (John Adams), 1843-1917.; Egleston, Thomas, 1832-1900; Elder, Cyrus, 1833-1912.; Holley, Alexander Lyman, 1832-1882.; Hotchkiss, Jedediah, 1828-1899.; Hutton, William R., 1846-1906.; Kunz, George Frederick, 1856-1932.; Low, Seth, 1850-1916.; Mackintosh, James Buckton, 1856-1891.; Potter, William Bleeker, 1846-1914.; Ricketts, Palmer C. (Palmer Chamberlain), 1856-1934.; Waldo, Leonard, b. 1853.; Architecture.; Mining engineering.; Metallurgy.; Architectural drawings.; Bills.; Blueprints.; Catalogs.; Checks.; Diagrams.; Engravings.; Invoices.; Letter books.; Lists.; Maps.; Photographs.; Prospectuses.; Receipts.; Reports.; Technical drawings.; Wills.; College teachers.; Metallurgists.; Mineralogists.; Mining engineers.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
Collection is shelved on-site.
Acquisition
1900 M-1900 Egleston, Thomas Bequest
1977 M-1977 Letterbook, 1864-69 Lamont-Doherty Geoscience Library Transfer
02/--/1997 M-97-02 Oversize drawings & engravings Columbiana Transfer
Selected Related Material-- At Columbia
Columbia University School of Mines Records, Rare book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: Correspondence, 1868-1901
  The Correspondence series consists of professional correspondence. Most of the letters are incoming correspondence, but the series does include one letterbook of Egleston's outgoing correspondence, and carbons of some of his correspondence with Seth Low, President of Columbia University during the latter part of Egleston's tenure at the school.
  - Austin, T.S., 1890 (Box 1)
  - Baclè, L., 1899 (Box 1)
  - Blei-und Silberwerk bei Bad-Ems, 1872 (Box 1)
  - Blood, Aretas, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Boehler Frères & Cie., 1896 (Box 1)
  - Bullman, Charles, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Casartelli, Joseph, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Chalmers, William James, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Church, John Adams, 1868-1869 (Box 1)
  - Clements, J.B., 1896 (Box 1)
  - Constable, C., 1878 (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Benjamin, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Davenport, R.W., 1885 (Box 1)
  - Dresler, H., 1874 (Box 1)
  - Dwight, A.S., 1891 (Box 1)
  - Egleston, Thomas
    - Letterbook (Box 1)
    - Letters relating to his bequest to Columbia University, 1897-1901 (Box 1)
  - Elder, Cyrus, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Engelhardt, E.N., 1887 (Box 1)
  - Garnkirk Fire Clay Co., 1885 (Box 1)
  - Gersdorf, Theodor, 1885-1892 (Box 1)
  - H., 1873-1893 (Box 1)
  - Henning, Gus C., 1886 (Box 1)
  - Holley, Alexander, 1871 (Box 1)
  - Hotchkiss, Jedediah, 1879 (Box 1)
  - Hutton, William R., 1879 (Box 1)
  - Iles, Malvern W., 1884 (Box 1)
  - Innerberger Hauptgewerkschaft, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Jones, William R., 1879 (Box 1)
  - Knapp, John. A., 1876 (Box 1)
  - Koga, Yoshimasa, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Kunz. George Frederick, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Lounsbery, R.P., 1892 (Box 1)
  - Low, Seth, 1890-1900 (Box 1)
    (contains Low's letters to Egleston, as well as carbon copies of Egleston's letters to Low)
  - Mackintosh, James Buckton, 1886-1887 (Box 1)
  - Macleod, John, 1886 (Box 1)
  - MacMartin, Arch., 1869 (Box 1)
  - Morgan Crucible Co. Ltd., 1895 (Box 1)
  - Morris, J.L., 1885 (Box 1)
  - Orsat, H., 1875 (Box 1)
  - Page, Walter T., 1888 (Box 1)
  - Pearce, Richard, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Rail Road Co., 1885 (Box 1)
  - Perry, R.S., 1895 (Box 1)
  - Potter, William Bleeker, 1889-1893 (Box 1)
  - Prosser, Thomas, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Ricketts, Palmer Chamberlaine, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Roberts-Austen, Sir William Chandler, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Russell, Edward H., 1894 (Box 1)
  - Schermerhorn, Frederick Augustus, 1875 (Box 1)
  - Schmidz, A., 1871 (Box 1)
  - Sewell, G.W., 1886 (Box 1)
  - Slade, Frederick J., 1871 (Box 1)
  - Sturtevant, B.F., 1888 (Box 1)
  - Terhune, R.H., 1887-1888 (Box 1)
  - Towne, Henry Robinson, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Vultè, Hermann Theodore, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Waldo, Leonard, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Winslow, Griswold & Holley, 1866 (Box 1)
  - Witherbee, T.F., 1872 (Box 1)
  - Young, Bennett Henderson, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Young, Edward S., 1887 (Box 1)
- Series II: Research and Documents, undated and 1868
  The Research and Documents series is comprised of printed material related to metallurgy that Egleston collected, as well as Egleston's professional work such as metallurgical analyses and some of his student work from his time at the Ecole Imperiale des Mines, Paris.
  - Cornwall, Henry Bedinger-- Catalogue and Description of the Freiberg Metallurgical Collection, 1868 (Box 1)
  - Egleston, Thomas
    - Architectural Drawings and Engravings (Box Oversize)
    - Technical Drawings (Box Oversize)
      (created by Egleston while a student at the Ecole Imperiale des Mines, Paris)
    - Maps and Prospectuses of Iron and Coal Land in Virginia and West Virginia (Box Oversize)
    - Metallurgical Analyses (Box 1)
    - Printed Ephemera, (2 Folders) (Box 1)
- Series III: Metric System Materials, 1893-1895
  This series consists of material arguing in favor of the United States moving to the metric system. The series includes correspondence between Egleston and other metric advocates, as well as published pamphlets, speeches, and reports relating to the metric system and its uses and advantages.
  - Correspondence, 1893-1895 (Box 2)
  - Documents and Pamphlets Related to the Metric System
    - Report of Charles W. Stone on Metric System (Box 2)
    - Letter from the Secretary of the Treasury Regarding the Adoption of the Metric System (Box 2)
    - House Bill for Exclusive Use of Metric System in Customs Service (Box 2)
    - Pamphlet-- Lord Kelvin on the Metric System (Box 2)
    - List of Bodies Which Have Approved the Metric System in the US (Box 2)
    - American Standards of Length Report on Methods and Results of the Metric System (Box 2)
    - Pamphlet-- "The Metric System" by T.C. Mendenhall (Box 2)
    - Speech of Charles Sumner on the Metric System (Box 2)
    - "Metric Coinage"-- Report to the U.S. House of Representatives (Box 2)
    - Proceedings of the American Metrological Society, 1873 (Box 2)
    - International Meridian Conference, Message of President, 1888 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints of Proposed Wire Gauge (Box 2)
    - Proposed U.S. Standard Gauges, (3 Folders) (Box 2)
    - Relation of Proposed Metric and Mechanical Engineers, (2 Folders) (Box 2)
    - Gradations for the New Decimal Gauge (Box 2)
    - Ephemera Related to Metric System